<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the loves of Lysander and Sabina a novel.</title>
            <title>Lisander</title>
            <author>T. S., fl. 1681-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1329</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12686926</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12686926</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65788</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65788)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 367:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the loves of Lysander and Sabina a novel.</title>
                  <title>Lisander</title>
                  <author>T. S., fl. 1681-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 137, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by J. Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First published as: Lisander, or, The souldier of fortune. 1681.</note>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: T.S.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE LOVES OF LYSANDER AND SABINA; A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>J. Taylor,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in S. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:2"/>
            <head>To the Deſerving and Ingenious <hi>William Forreſter</hi> of <hi>Dottel</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY <hi>Liſander</hi> that never us'd to beg any bodies Protection but that of the Ladies, now caſts himſelf at your feet, and humbly ſues for yours. If his <hi>Engliſh</hi> be none of the fineſt-ſpun, I deſire you would remember he has been a Souldier and a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller: and if the miſtakes in
<pb facs="tcp:65788:3"/> his Conduct cannot now and then eſcape without obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I would have other men learn Wiſdom at his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and make uſe of thoſe Rocks whereon he ſplit, for Sea-marks. I never deſign'd to draw his Character ſo great, that like <hi>Pantagruel</hi>'s Doublet it ſhould fit no body elſe; it is far ſhort of that which our men of Wit are us'd to give their brain-born Hero's, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thought it dangerous to Addreſs himſelf to any but a very Candid <hi>Mecaenas.</hi> Such, I am very well aſſur'd, you are, and for fear of being miſtaken, I have all the Kingdom on my ſide.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:3"/>
            <p>But your early Honours both Civil and Military have ſav'd me the labour of a Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, (the ordinary entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Dedications) and only left me room to ſay, 'tis pity your Vertue is ſo ſingular, and that your merit has no more Emulators.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation that ever I made, and it may be the firſt that ever you receiv'd; and if you chance to meet with any thing in theſe Maiden ſheets that ſhall pleaſe, I ſhall think my pen has loſt her Virginity with honour, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to arrogate to my ſelf the Mighty Title of an Author,
<pb facs="tcp:65788:4"/> only for having the honour of ſo great a Patron.</p>
            <p>All that remains now Sir, is to beg your Pardon, for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring to prefix your name to ſuch a Triflle without your leaſt knowledg or Conſent: All the excuſe I can make is this, I did it without making you acquainted, that you might hear it condemn'd without bluſhing, and never think your ſelf in the leaſt concern'd to defend the Errours of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65788:4"/>
            <head>LISANDER, Or the SOULDIER OF FORTUNE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey that have taken pains to digeſt Moral Philoſophy into a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or Syſtem of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, have always aſſign'd Virtue the middle place between two Extremes. And yet methinks, a very little Logick, more than what we ſuck from our Nurſes, might ſhew a man of Senſe ſuch knots, and difficulties in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65788:5"/> aſſertion, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelf (were he alive again) might find enough to do to reſolve. For Example, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, and Prodigality are the Extremes of Liberality: and ſo are Cowardize and Fool-hardineſs of Fortitude: and yet we muſt confeſs, that both theſe Exceſſes are the more eaſily corrected, and ſo nearer to the Mean than either of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary defects: Otherwiſe the terms of Magnificent, and Heroick (which in all Ages have met with ſuch a profound reſpect) could never be either neceſſary, or ſutable to the Character of a Great man. Were it not to give my Reader occaſion of ſuſpecting my own inclinations, I might ſay as much of the exceſs of Love, which though it have driven many out of the beaten paths, and methods which the ſeverer precepts of our Grand-fathers have deſign'd, yet can the moſt of thoſe Truants ſay, and the World will ſubſcribe to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65788:5"/> them beſides, that they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly been perſons of the fineſt Spirits, and the greateſt Souls, and have done ſuch things, as may juſtly challenge an honourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, as long as brave Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have any Golden Legends, and which it may be) they had never ſo much as enterpriz'd, under any other Conduct, but that of the Blind God.</p>
            <p>I do not offer you this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, as an entire and abſolute Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of all thoſe extravagances, which the Gentleman, that furniſhes the ſubject of this Story, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have been guilty of, but only to mitigate the ſeverity of your cenſures, and to allay the rigour of your Juſtice, with a little gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous tenderneſs, and compaſſion. I will urge this Addreſs on his behalf with no other Argument, but that common Principle of Self-intereſt, which every one finds ſo deep engraven in his own breaſt.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65788:6"/> For how can any man think, if by chance he ſhould be overtaken with the like ſurprize, to obtain that pity, and connivance himſelf, which he has diſcourteouſly deni'd to others: And if he ſhall tell me, he is in no danger, and that he is out of ſhot of thoſe childiſh Arms, I dare ſay he does not conſider in the mean while, what an unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward imputation he lays upon his good nature, or what an unmanly violence he does his Reaſon, while all the world muſt needs cenſure him for a deſperate Opiniator, that will not believe his Houſe is as combuſtible as his Neighbours, till he ſee it on fire about his ears.</p>
            <p>To keep you no longer in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe, It ſhall ſuffice me to tell you, that our Adventurer (whom in this Relation we ſhall call <hi>Liſander</hi>) was a Gentleman of our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, of an Ancient, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Family, and it may be the firſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65788:6"/> of his Houſe, that for four Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations had croſs'd the Seas with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leave of his Friends, and a competent Subſiſtence. The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this bold Deſign has been ſomething uncertainly reported, but they that were of his Secrets, (and he himſelf ſince) tell us, that meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſome oppoſition in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, which neither pleas'd his nor the Ladies Friends, after a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious reſiſtance of the two contrary Paſſions of Love and Anger, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween which his Soul was diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and torn in pieces) he found himſelf unequal to the burden, and therefore reſolv'd to try, if croſſing the Seas, he could leave his Cares on this ſide the water. His heart was too great to think of any other Employment, than the Sword; and ſo the War betwixt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> gave him a fair opportunity. <hi>Liſander</hi> had I know not what natural Averſion to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65788:7"/> the <hi>French</hi> Nation, notwithſtanding that Fortune and Victory at that time ſeem'd to have undertaken the Conduct of their Arms; and therefore reſolves to ſerve the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> The apprehenſions of hard Duty, and bad Pay, and all thoſe Difficulties, which one that has ſerv'd there knows but too well, and a man in his Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances might very reaſonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, had been enough to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr'd any body, but <hi>Liſander,</hi> from the enterpriſe: and yet the heat of his Youth, and the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Mind, with the deſire he had of ſcowring thoſe honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Arms, which one of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours had purchas'd againſt the <hi>French</hi> at the famous Battel of <hi>Agincourt,</hi> eaſily contemn'd, and ſurmounted theſe diſadvantages.</p>
            <p>Thus he, and the Lady of his Vows, whoſe name was <hi>Sabina,</hi> (after a thouſand Prayers, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65788:7"/> to divert him from this rough, deſign loſt, and thrown away) took leave one of another. They parted with the ſame pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sighs, and troubled Silence, that Souls leave their Bodies in the Agony of their diſſolution. Something they would both of them have ſaid, but ſuch was their ſurpriſing grief, that their Paſſion found no vent. Tears, and Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were the laſt, and only Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Expreſſions of their croſs Love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liſander</hi> when he divided him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and went one half for the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> was about Twenty years old.</p>
            <p>His complexion was not quite ſo clear as that of a womans, but the Features, and Lineaments of his face were pleaſing, and Majeſtick to Admiration. Nature was ſo kind to him, that he neither wanted, nor wore a Periwig, for (as if ſhe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65788:8"/> had fore-ſeen his Military deſign) She had given him a lovely head of brown Hair, curl'd all in ſuch rings, as the Ladies of the laſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration call'd Heart-breakers. He was ſomething taller than the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſort of men, and ſo delicately well limb'd, and ſhap'd to his height, that you would have thought Nature had intended him only for a Pattern. His very Meen, and Preſence had always ſomething in them of Noble, and if ever he had deni'd his blood, would have been ſure to have given him the lie. But which made every body won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) he had a particular way of wearing his Clothes, though nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor any body elſe knew where the ſecret lay; for whatever Suit he had on, became him a great deal better than richer Clothes did another man. He had already paſs'd five years in one of the Inns of Court, where you may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65788:8"/> be ſure he had learn'd to know which Pocket his money was in, and how many two and two are, without a Conjurer. His Natural Abilities (without which 'tis impoſſible to be excellent in any thing) were ſuch, as drew every bodies eyes upon him, whatever he did or ſaid. He was of a ſtrong, and piercing Judgment, a ready Wit, a moſt undaunted Conſtancy and Reſolution, an indefatigable Diligence, and of a wonderful quick Diſpatch. In a word, take him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, he was a man of a moſt becoming and Gentile Addreſs, and all his Actions were accompanied with a certain fatal agreeableneſs, for which we have no name. Only his Diſpoſition was a little too ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible of that ſweet Poyſon, that gentle Torment, that deſirable Evil, and almoſt inſeparable Plague of a great Mind, Love, which would now and then be a little too
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65788:9"/> buſie in his Management, often ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Minutes from a ſerious hour, and ſpoiling a good nights reſt after a hard days labour.</p>
            <p>Heaven, and the Sea were loath to cruſh ſo brave a Spirit in the ſetting forth, and ſo he arriv'd at <hi>Dunkirk</hi> (once an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garriſon) in one Afternoon, where the next Morning he took leave of the Maſter of the Veſſel, and with his Horſe, and a hundred Broad-pieces, which was all his Stock, ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> (where the General of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forces was at that time) to lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his Fortune of War.</p>
            <p>His arrival at the out-guards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gates of the City, did him the Office of a Court Addreſs, and without any of thoſe prelimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Solemnities, which are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily made uſe of to introduce men into the preſence of a Prince, the cuſtom of bringing Strangers to be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65788:9"/> examin'd whence they come, and what their buſineſs is, was his ſafe Conduct to the General. It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, that the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Reſident at the Court was at that time attending the General about ſome buſineſs of his Maſters, and ſo very opportunely ſerv'd for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter between the General and <hi>Liſander.</hi> It is ſtrange to obſerve what a gentle influence Beauty has upon all mens affections, and how inſenſibly it makes it ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our wills, for no ſooner had <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> told him his inclinations, but the General was over-joy'd to ſee a Gentleman of his Breeding, and appearance come to offer his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the War. And being well aſſur'd of his Parts and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by the pertinence and good manage of his Addreſs, receiv'd him with greater Demonſtrations of Courteſie, and more Affability than the manner of that grave Nation,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65788:10"/> and the height of their Spirits does ordinarily vouchſafe. And as he was about to Conſult with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, which way, or what Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod he ſhould uſe to ſerve this Young Gentleman in his pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (ſeeing he had never born Arms) A <hi>Spaniſh Maeſtro di Campo,</hi> or Colonel of the Army, that was juſt come from <hi>Gant,</hi> where his Regiment lay, and had heard all the Diſcourſe, told his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence (not without ſome Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that there was an <hi>Alfier,</hi> or Enſigns Commiſſion in his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſpoſe of, and if the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman (in regard it was a proper and an honourable Office for a perſon of Quality to learn the Trade of War in) pleas'd to accept it, and his Excellence would give leave, he would think himſelf extremely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd, and promis'd that he would take a moſt particular Charge of him, as if he were his own Son;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65788:10"/> ſuch a mighty impreſſion and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valence had the very Preſence, and Addreſs of <hi>Liſander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The motion was very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble on all ſides, only the General told <hi>Liſander,</hi> he was almoſt aſham'd to make him ſo little an offer, but if he pleas'd to content himſelf till he was acquainted with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue, and the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of War, he doubted not but to find means to do ſomething for him which might deſerve his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance. <hi>Liſander</hi> made him a handſome and grave return of his Compliment, and told him that he was too ſenſible of his own want of merit, not to underſtand the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he was pleas'd to do him, and that he would ſtudy to avoid the imputation of an ingrate, more than he would the preſervation of his Life. That very night he accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied his Colonel towards <hi>Gant,</hi> who was almoſt extaſied with his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65788:11"/> good Fortune, and verily believ'd his good Angel had taken care to Conduct him into the Generals pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in that lucky Conjuncture.</p>
            <p>Four whole years did <hi>Liſander</hi> ſerve in that Regiment, in which time (young as he was) he made a ſhift (almoſt without aemula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to run through all the Charges, and Offices from an Enſign, to a Lieutenant Colonel. And acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf in them all with ſo much Integrity, Conduct, and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, that the whole Army was full of his name, and nothing trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them ſo much, as that our He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro had not been born a <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they lay in Winter-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Liſander</hi> (who as I told you was Amorous enough, and the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt man alive to be ſo) to divert the trouble which he conceiv'd for the abſence of his dear Miſtreſs, did ordinarily paſs a good part of his ſpare hours with the Ladies of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65788:11"/> beſt Character, and Quality in the Town, and was every where ſo wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and his Company ſo much deſir'd, that oftentimes it bred ſuch little heats, and Animoſities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, as without doubt had been more publick, and made more noiſe in the world, but for fear of doing violence to their Modeſty. And by this means he never wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the choiſeſt Laces and Linnen which the Country (famous for thoſe Commodities) could afford, or any thing elſe (in reaſon) which the Ladies had to diſpoſe of.</p>
            <p>And when Summer came, that the Army was to March into the Field, it would ee'n have griev'd any bodies heart to ſee with what a Catholick ſorrow (as if the Sun had gone the wrong way) they receiv'd the killing news of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture. And which yet extremely aggravated the diſaſter, their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion durſt not complain, or ſhow
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65788:12"/> their grievance in Publick, though among Confidents, and in ſeveral little Cabals, his name was the ordinary Entertainment, both of Song, and Drink, and Company.</p>
            <p>And as often as any fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and ſafe conveyance offer'd it ſelf, it was ten to one he had ſome of their <hi>Billets douces</hi> and ſure 'tis more than pity they are ſo many of them loſt. I will only give you one in paſſing ſent him by a <hi>German</hi> Lady (as you will ſee) upon ſome March or other, which I have accidentally recover'd out of the mercileſs jaws of time, as well to teſtifie my obligations to, as aſſert the honour of the Nation, and to convince you they were only <hi>French</hi> men that made <hi>Parler comme un Alemàn</hi> to ſignifie, to ſpeak like a Fool. The lines are in effect theſe.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65788:12"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>SInce Fate Commands and we muſt part,</l>
                  <l>Farewel thou Conquerour of my heart,</l>
                  <l>Farewel the Kindeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man</l>
                  <l>That ever cros't the Ocean;</l>
                  <l>Farewel that Face, that hath betray'd</l>
                  <l>The Honour of a <hi>German</hi> Maid;</l>
                  <l>Yet wer't to do again, I know</l>
                  <l>I had no power to ſay thee no.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I tremble ſtill at thoſe Alarms</l>
                  <l>That ſhook my Lover from my Arms,</l>
                  <l>A Maidens Curſes be his doom</l>
                  <l>That firſt invented Fife and Drum,</l>
                  <l>Curs'd be his Name, who ere begun</l>
                  <l>This Quarrelling with Pike and Gun;</l>
                  <l>Methinks a Tryal at the Bar</l>
                  <l>Were eaſier than this Trade of War.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cruel <hi>Bellona,</hi> now I gueſs</l>
                  <l>Thou envied'ſt my happyneſs;</l>
                  <l>The Gentle Youth thy Breaſt did move,</l>
                  <l>And thou waſt fall'n thy Self in Love:</l>
                  <l>O uſe him well, and with thy Shield</l>
                  <l>Protect his Perſon in the Field,</l>
                  <l>For know dear Goddeſs if he fall</l>
                  <l>The ſelf-ſame Wound kills me and all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What pity 'twere that Crimſon juice</l>
                  <l>Should only Plants and Flow'rs produce,</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65788:13"/>
                  <l>Whoſe every drop might get a Line</l>
                  <l>Of Nobler worthies than the Nine.</l>
                  <l>How full of fear is Love! and yet</l>
                  <l>If Beauty, Honour, Valour, Wit,</l>
                  <l>Can ſave a man from Deſtiny,</l>
                  <l>And brave the Fates, I'm ſure 'tis he.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then let your Death-charg'd Engines fly,</l>
                  <l>Let Ball, and Thunder fill the sky</l>
                  <l>Let Rivers ſwell with ſhowres of blood,</l>
                  <l>The Earth grow drunk with th' purple flood,</l>
                  <l>The God of War ſhall Guard his Son,</l>
                  <l>Till theſe unfriendly days are done,</l>
                  <l>And then we'll Sacrifice one Kiſs</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Venus</hi> Health, and one to His.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Till then may Victory and Fate</l>
                  <l>Conſpire to make you Fortunate,</l>
                  <l>And may bright Honour ever reſt</l>
                  <l>As in her Center on your Creſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall a brazen Statue be</l>
                  <l>Enough to tell Poſterity</l>
                  <l>Your Worth: a ſofter way ſhall raiſe</l>
                  <l>A living Image to your praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="24 pages">
               <desc>〈24 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:14"/>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65788:14"/>
            <p> (like a man that wanted Lodging) from one houſe to another, as long as people were up, and then from one Guard to another, till day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, which drove him to his Quarters, leſt the world ſhould have taken notice of his diſorder. He us'd all the means he thought ſafe, or proper, to inform himſelf who this Beauty might be, but all prov'd ineffectual. And now he began to repent he had not exchang'd his Office, with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonel, that ſo he might have had time to find his new Miſtreſs, and with his own dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence make himſelf amends for the rigour of his hard Fate. Reſtleſs, and full of thought as he was, he roſe from his bed before he had well warm'd it, chang'd his Clothes, and (under colour of taking leave) viſited moſt of the Ladies in the Town, to ſee if he might find her in any of their Companies.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65788:15"/> But he beſtow'd all his labour in vain, and only wearied himſelf againſt his March, which was to begin the ſame Afternoon. About two of the Clock the Drums beat, and the Regiment drew up in the Market-place. At length came the Lieutenant-Colonel attended with the Magiſtrates, and Gentry of the Town, to take a ſolemn leave. His trouble was ſuch that it might eaſily be read in his very looks. And every body knowing he was a man of ſuch Spirit, and Reſolution, could not but wonder, that ſo ſmall a matter, as changing the Countrey (which was his own Election beſides) ſhould affect him ſo much, without ever hitting, or ſo much as ſuſpecting the true cauſe of his Diſcompoſure. Sorry they were (though they lov'd no Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers) to part with <hi>Liſander,</hi> his temper had ſo little in it of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inſolence (though he had
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65788:15"/> ſerv'd long enough among them to have learn'd it,) and therefore to teſtifie their reſpects they waited on him about a League out of Town, and then with a whole Volly of warm Prayers committed him to the Conduct, and favour of his good Fortune. He was glad they were gone. For, though their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would otherwiſe have been moſt grateful, and pleaſing, yet as his heart beat at that time, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment was unneceſſary, and the honour was troubleſome. Solitude had been a fitter Companion, and the ſhade of ſome ancient Wood or the bank of ſome conſidering Stream would better have ſuited the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his Grief, than a matter of Twenty ſtarch'd <hi>Aldermen</hi> with <hi>Spaniſh</hi>-leather Boots, and <hi>Holland</hi>-boot-hoſe-tops, with every one a mouthful of Wind, and an old Beaver full of Smoak. In vain did his Officers ſtrive to ſhorten the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65788:16"/> day with a Bottle, or a Song, or a Story, or any new Amours they met with in the March. He was never ſo much at his eaſe, as when he was alone, and could complain without being over-heard. Many a time when he was a convenient ſpace either before, or behind the Regiment, he would begin thus with himſelf. The Gods have ſeen, and reveng'd thy wrongs, and my Cruelty (My dear <hi>Sabina,</hi> the firſt, and only conſtant Miſtreſs of my Vows, and Wiſhes,) making all thoſe Wounds, which were given me by thy firſt Beauty, pain me, and bleed again by the guilty touch of this laſt. With what aſſurance, what <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> or excuſes can I ever think of returning to thee, after the Errors, and voluntary Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of four whole years?</p>
            <p>And, as if I had yet a mind in ſome meaſure to proportion the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65788:16"/> diſtance of place, to the length of time, I am now running two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms further from thee. Forgive me dear <hi>Sabina,</hi> this acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is but counterfeit, and I do but flatter both thee, and my ſelf with a repentance which in ſpite of my reſolution is but falſe and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial. My Vows, my Vertue, my Faith, my Conſtancy, have all forſaken me. And (though Fate in pity to thee have remov'd the Object) yet have I no truce with my Paſſion. The Beauty of her Perſon, the Sharpneſs of her Wit, her becoming her Addreſs, like ſo many Familiar Spirits have taken poſſeſſion of my breaſt, and haunt my imagination day and night. But above all her Courteſie which (if one might interpet ambiguities to advantage) I ſhould call Love, has pierc'd my very Soul, and has in it, ſuch Charms as ſure a colder conſtitution, and a ſeverer vertue,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65788:17"/> than that of mine could never have been able to reſiſt. Once indeed I thought I dream'd, I talk'd of nothing but <hi>Sabina;</hi> and vainly reſolv'd in ſpite of all the little ſtops, and lets I might meet with in the way, to carry the reſpect I had for her, pure, and undivided to my Grave.</p>
            <p>But length of time (I ſee) and abſence (which is my own ſin) has almoſt obliterated thoſe old Idea's. 'Tis this Stranger, this new Face, (which I, alas! muſt never, never ſee again) which has given me my mortal Wound. And yet I am reſolv'd, that as ſoon as I have deliver'd the Regiment at <hi>Barcellona,</hi> and obtain'd my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, I will, I muſt return to <hi>Flanders</hi> in queſt of that Face, whoſe Smiles, and Frowns deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the iſſues of my life and death.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:65788:17"/>
            <p>Theſe and ſuch like were the paſtimes of his Solitude. For as all other Melancholy in its deepeſt, and moſt retired ſpeculations is not without ſome mixture of pleaſure, and ſatisfaction; ſo eſpecially in Love, the contemplation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of a Beauty we have lov'd, (though unſuccesfully) fills, and extends the heart with warm blood, and freſh ſpirits even in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair it ſelf. And this was the only conſolation, which never quitted the perplexed <hi>Liſander</hi> in all his march to <hi>Barcellona.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Colonel and <hi>Clarinda</hi> made ſeveral little ſtops in their Journey through <hi>France,</hi> but the Love-ſick Lady found nothing there, that pleas'd her. Now and then ſhe met with ſome Amorous Addreſſes, and thoſe from Perſons very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable too, but they only ſerv'd to fan, and blow the Fire which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65788:18"/> 
               <hi>Liſander</hi> had kindled in her boſom, and which had now ſeiz'd upon her very bones, and marrow. Every new City furniſh'd her with new Admirers, but their Applications always recoyl'd into their own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, and did them moſt miſchief at the rebound. <hi>Clarinda</hi> ſtood like a Rock in vain importun'd by the Waves, all the effect their fine ſpeeches had with her, was only to teach her how to ſet a juſt value upon her ſelf. Seven days after the Colonels arrival at <hi>Barcellona,</hi> came <hi>Liſander</hi> with the weary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment.</p>
            <p>He was welcom to the Colonel as an Angel, and he deſerv'd to be ſo indeed, not only for his former good Service, but for his ready compliance with him to leave <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and the great diſcretion and diligence he had us'd in the March. The day that the Regiment arriv'd,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65788:18"/> the Lieutenant-Colonel, and ſome other of the Officers, din'd with the Colonel, when after Dinner drinking a Glaſs of Wine (rather like Souldiers than <hi>Spaniards) Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> (as if his good Angel had whiſper'd him ſomething in his Ear) was obſerv'd to be gayer, and liker himſelf than he had been all the March. <hi>Clarinda,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Ceremony of <hi>Spain,</hi> was not ſeen among the Gentlemen at Dinner, but eat in her own Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where the Servants were ſo laviſh in repreſenting <hi>Liſanders</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments, that the talk caſt her into a deep ſit of Melancholy, with bringing to her mind the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of that man whom ſhe could never forget. When the Company parted <hi>Liſander</hi> was invited to lodge there till he was provided of convenient Quarters; and you may eaſily believe that when he accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65788:19"/> the motion, <hi>Venus</hi> and her Son ſmil'd at the Omen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liſander</hi> had heard of <hi>Clarinda</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and underſtood that ſhe was now at home with her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but little did he think, that ſhe was the Lady, that had coſt him all the quiet, and content he had in the World, for theſe laſt two months. However to do his breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right, he reſolv'd to Court the firſt opportunity, to bear up to her, and make her a Reverence. The next morning at a good hour (as if the Deſtinies had now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of their anger, and were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to make our Lovers ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for their paſt ſufferings) <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> went to walk in the Garden, where <hi>Liſander,</hi> as he was dreſſing himſelf in his Chamber, was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aware of her. At another time he had needed no other admoniſher
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65788:19"/> to diſpatch, and make himſelf rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the encounter, than the warmth of his own temper, and inclination, though now, the laſt impreſſion his heart had receiv'd, made him uſe the occaſion with a great deal of indifference. As ſoon as ever <hi>Liſander</hi> enter'd the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, (ſays the Governante, who was waiting on <hi>Clarinda</hi>) Here's the Lieutenant-Colonel, (for ſhe had ſeen him, and deſcrib'd him to the young Lady (as I was ſaying) the day before,) and as modeſty and good manners oblig'd them, they walk'd ſoftly into a by-Walk, as it had been on purpoſe to avoid him, for it was early, and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was in her morning Dreſs. <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> thought it no point of his civility to go directly the next way up to them, (as if he had had no other deſign in the Garden) but intended to drop on them, as it were by chance, and ſo he began
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65788:20"/> to round them, as one would do a Covy of Partridge. He was juſt come ſo near, that <hi>Clarinda</hi> knew him to be the ſame Gentleman, ſhe had ſeen at the Play at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> though, by the favour of her morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dreſs, he knew not her. And juſt as he pull'd off his Hat, and ſaid, <hi>Good morrow fair Ladies,</hi> the Colonel who had been taking the Freſco, ſteps forth of an Arbour at the end of the Walk, and ſaluted him, they two fell immediately into Diſcourſe, which gave <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> a fair occaſion to march off, without making him any anſwer, but a Curteſie. She was certainly much beholding to her morning Cloths, and more to the ſeaſonable interruption of her Father, for the prevention of that ſurprize and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order which muſt needs have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the diſcovery on both ſides, and infallibly have given the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernante who was well acquainted
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65788:20"/> with the vanities of this wicked World) juſt occaſion to ſuſpect, even more than the very truth. As they walk'd off, the Governante ask'd <hi>Clarinda,</hi> What think you now of my judgment? Is it not as I told you? Is not the Lieutenant-Colonel a very fine man? Has he not a brave Port? And twenty other little Queſtions of the ſame ſort, to which when ſhe obſerv'd <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> made no anſwer, and ſeem'd not to mind her: She went on laughing, I warrant your heart has taken wing already, and you are in love with him at firſt ſight. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (ſays <hi>Clarinda</hi>) if one may be forgiven for falling in love with any man at firſt ſight, this is he; for I think him the handſomeſt, and goodlieſt perſon of a man, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I ſaw in my life. You have reaſon, (ſays the Governante) and I muſt confeſs, that ſuch ſights to a young Lady in a morning next
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65788:21"/> her heart, are oftentimes of very dangerous conſequence. What dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence do you mean (ſays <hi>Clarinda</hi>)? As long as La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies confine themſelves within the Laws, and Obligations of their Sex, what danger can there be in an Honourable Love? The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernante preſently fancy'd (and well ſhe might) that <hi>Liſander</hi>'s preſence had a little mov'd the young Lady, but ſhe never ſo much as dream'd of any former Acquaintance. For though ſhe had been with her in <hi>Flanders,</hi> yet the night, that the young Lovers encounter'd one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the Play, ſhe was not with them, for ſhe was buſie putting things in readineſs for the Journey. Though ſince their Arrival at <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellona,</hi> (being well aſſur'd of the Governant's diſcretion, and finding ſome kind of eaſe in the bare Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Love) <hi>Clarinda</hi> had told her the whole Story. When
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65788:21"/> they were come into her Chamber, ſhe bad the Governant ſhut the Door, and calling her to her, to the Bed ſide, with her face, as full of paſſion, and tranſport as her heart could hold, Dear <hi>Leonora,</hi> (ſays ſhe) This is the Gentleman. And with that, a ſudden ſhower of Tears, and an impetuous Storm of Sighs made her ſenſes retire for ſhelter, and threw her tender <hi>Body</hi> pale, and breathleſs on the Bed, where there was neither help, nor company (the more the pity) but the frighted <hi>Leonora.</hi> She ran pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and call'd two or three of the Maids, and by that time <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> was come to her ſelf again. This was rather the tranſport, and exceſs of joy, than any thing elſe, for now the day began to break up, and ſhe began to conceive fair hopes of that love which the Stars ſeem'd to favour, as if they had mov'd by her direction. And therefore, as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65788:22"/> ſoon as ſhe had taken a little Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Water, and the Maids were ſent away, ſhe began, and told her diſcreet Confident the <hi>Bruſſels</hi> Story (with all the circumſtances ſhe thought neceſſary to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the preſent buſineſs) over again. And now the matter is brought upon the Carpet, and a Conſult is held, what is to be done, or what Meaſures are to be taken in their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing they agreed on, was to paſs an irrevocable ſentence againſt raſhneſs, and precipitancy in the caſe: And ſo they reſolv'd, becauſe (now there were no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Strangers, beſides the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-Colonel, who lodg'd there) ſhe would be expected at Dinner, her indiſpoſition ſhould excuſe her for that day. This was done on purpoſe that <hi>Liſander</hi> ſhould not ſee her at unawares, but that they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65788:22"/> might have time enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what methods they ſhould make uſe of for an Interview, leſt the ſurprize might give the World ſome untoward apprehenſions. All that day was waſted in uncertain Counſels, and nothing particular was determin'd, but that <hi>Clarinda</hi> ſhould make uſe of the firſt proper opportunity to make her ſelf known to him, and (ſince ſhe was now in <hi>Spain,</hi> and thought ſhe had him faſt enough) it was reſolv'd, ſhe ſhould treat him with more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and greater reſervation, than the firſt Encounter had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, which (that ſhe might ſtand fair in his opinion) was to be pretended only jeſt, and rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery.</p>
            <p>The Colonel, and <hi>Liſander</hi> in the Garden, diſcours'd the whole ſtory of the March, wherein <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> was obſerv'd to deliver him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65788:23"/> all along with ſo much cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and indifference, that being modeſtly urg'd, he told the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel plainly, that he repented the Expedition, and had a deſign to pretend his <hi>Ben' Servito,</hi> or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his Majeſty, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
            <p>The Colonel (as much as he could without entering into his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets) endeavour'd to diſwade him, ſtriving to poſſeſs him with good thoughts of the Country, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before him the fair proſpect he had of raiſing his Fortunes in <hi>Spain,</hi> whereas the <hi>Netherlands</hi> wanted that choice, and variety of great Employments either in Peace, or War. In ſhort the Colonel laid before him ſo many reaſons of weight, interwoven with ſuch to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his good will, and ſo much paſſion for his converſation, that, before they parted, <hi>Liſander</hi> (tho
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65788:23"/> he was well enough reſolv'd within himſelf) in complaiſance to the Colonel (becauſe he ſaw what trouble it gave him) was fain to tell him, he would conſider of it. The Colonel had more than a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and on his Journey too, thought of a Match betwixt the Lieutenant-Colonel, and his Daughter: And to ſay the truth, almoſt as oft as he look'd upon her in the Coach, within himſelf, he could ee'n have wiſh'd her fairly in <hi>Liſander</hi>'s Arms. And now finding his inclination to return for <hi>Flanders,</hi> (though he thought it inconſiſtent with his gravity to be ſeen in it) yet he reſolv'd to ſhew him the fair <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> at the beſt advantage, and try whether fleſh and blood (which were as warm in <hi>Liſander,</hi> as in another) could reſiſt the powerful charms of her Youth, and Beauty.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65788:24"/>
            <p>The next morning going to ſee his Daughter at her Chamber, and finding her pretty cheerful and hearty, he bid her dreſs her ſelf that day, and come to Dinner. She did ſo, and about an hour before Noon, either to get her an appetite, or to give <hi>Liſander</hi> time and place to accoſt her before Dinner, ſhe walk'd out into the Garden. As if every thing had conſpired to further her deſign, it happen'd to be Poſt-day, and ſo the Colonel having ſome Diſpatches to make, kept his Cloſet the moſt part of the forenoon. <hi>Liſander</hi> having the opportunity in his hands, went to congratulate the young Ladies Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and give her the reſt of that Addreſs, which the Colonel had interrupted in the beginning. As he came up to her, <hi>Clarinda</hi> (who was alone) was ſtooping down, and either gathering, or pretended to be gathering Flowers,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65788:24"/> with her back towards him. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam (ſays <hi>Liſander</hi> when he was come within four or five paces of her) I am glad to— whereupon <hi>Clarinda</hi> turning her head about, and looking on him, he could go no farther, but ſtood like one of the Statues in the Garden, that had ſtep'd from the Pedeſtal. He knew her (ſuch an impreſſion her face had made in his ſoul) as well as if he had never left her company, ſince the firſt time he had ſeen her, and was ſo thunder-ſtruck with the ſurprize, that except ſhe had pitty'd his diſorder, and ask'd him how he did, he had certainly remained longer in the Exſtaſie. As ſoon as he came a little to himſelf, he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to kiſs her hand, but ſhe, who had already reſolv'd to make him believe, ſhe did but railly him at the Play, drew back, and deni'd it, telling him with a ſmile, that the cuſtoms of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:65788:25"/> were different. Though the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys be different, (Madam ſays he) I hope your goodneſs is ſtill the ſame, and that your Ladiſhip cannot differ from your ſelf. No otherwiſe Sir (ſays ſhe) than what jeſt, and earneſt make the ſame Perſon differ. I remember I ſaw you at a Play at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and had a mind to make my ſelf merry with you, but, if that liberty of jeſt ſhall any ways influence your Addreſſes here in <hi>Spain,</hi> you muſt not take it ill, if you ſee me very ſeldom. Alaſs! (Madam ſayes he) how diſproportionate is it to the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Sex, to make your ſelf ſport at the expence of anothers ruine. For that jeſting (if you call it ſo) has undone me. And if your jeſt have ſuch power, and charms in it, what mortal ſtrength can reſiſt, or human force oppoſe it ſelf to your earneſt. The wound which that fatal Edge-tool gave
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65788:25"/> me at that time, had certainly kill'd me before this, but that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune (I ſee) has kept me alive to make her ſelf ſport. Sir (ſays ſhe ſmiling) I think ſhe has choſen a proper perſon for the Province, for you do it to a miracle, and 'tis pitty, but we were in ſome ſuch place, as we firſt met, that the happy Company might partake with us, and I not bluſh with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at you thus alone. And that's my grief, (Madam ſays he) but when I have told you, with a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers freedom, that I love you, that I have done ſo ever ſince I firſt ſaw you, and that I cannot chuſe but do ſo, as long as I live, laugh on in the name of Merriment, and know that my Paſſion is not the leſs ſerious for your turning it into Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule. Theſe laſt words ſhe thought were a little Cholerick, and Savoured of the Souldier, and therefore to let him ſee he had met
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65788:26"/> with his match: Pray Sir (ſays ſhe, bluſhing to think how ſhe play'd the Hypocrite) if you have any kindneſs for me, let me never hear one word more of it. You cannot chuſe but think, that at the Play, I had been told your Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, and who you were, and I hope you had wit enough to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>Irony:</hi> But if you are not convinc'd of your folly with a jeſt, yet pray be ſo, when I have told you, you are to blame in good earneſt, and ſo fare-ye-well. With that ſhe mended her pace, and walk'd very faſt towards the houſe, and he to keep himſelf in counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance (if any body ſhould by chance have ſeen them) march'd along with her, crying all the way (like an importunate Beggar) Nay dear Madam, Sweet Madam, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you Madam, But one word Madam: What's that Sir (ſays ſhe?) That you would forgive
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65788:26"/> (ſays he) what's paſt, and take no advantage of Poor <hi>Liſanders</hi> weakneſs. It is your future be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour (ſays ſhe) that muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your pardon, and your better Conduct in time to come, that muſt Apologize for your paſt weakneſs. Juſt as they came into the Hall, the Colonel (who was coming down to Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) met them, and ſo ſhe left them two together, and ran to her Chamber to tell the Governante the ſucceſs of the Encounter, and how ſhe had much ado to contain her ſelf, and forbear laughing in his face, to ſee him run along with her, like a Lacquay, Dear Madam, ſweet Madam, and ſo on.</p>
            <p>The Diſcourſe at Table was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided between the Colonel, and <hi>Liſander.</hi> The young Lady (which would have ſeem'd a little ſtrange to one that had heard her in the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65788:27"/> Garden, and were not well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Cuſtoms of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey) only fill'd a mute place, and gave a negligent Audience. <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> was that day a little more Airy than he had been ſince his Arrival, and the Colonel was well enough pleas'd to imagine, he was a little influenc'd by the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Daughter. And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd from that very moment, to give her more Liberty, than the Conduct of that wary Nation would allow, rather than <hi>Liſander</hi> ſhould want any honourable occaſion of cheriſhing the tender Sentiments he might begin to have for the Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Clarinda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That evening our <hi>Amoroſo</hi> took a walk all alone about the Town-walls, where his Encounter in the Garden with all its Circumſtances (as far as his confuſion gave him leave to remember) came freſh
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65788:27"/> into his thoughts. <hi>Clarinda</hi> he knew had the better of it, and yet he found himſelf well enough ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for the Defeat, with the unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected retrieve of the Lady, whoſe loſs had almoſt made him deſperate. He was not us'd to be non-ſuited in Addreſſes of that kind, which made him bear this with a great deal the more impatience. And (though he had Conduct enough to diſſemble it in Publick) her <hi>Spaniſh</hi> vertue, and ſeverity did but ſerve to Fan the fire, and make his Paſſion grow the more impetuous, and unruly.</p>
            <p>It was never ſo troubleſome to him, as when he was alone, and yet (which is none of the leaſt Plagues of an unfortunate Lover) he always ſtudied to avoid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. This deſire of Solitude, and ſome little indiſpoſition which his Melancholy had procur'd, kept him two, or three days in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65788:28"/> where 'tis impoſſible any man ſhould tell you how he paſs'd his time, or what he endur'd, but he, that has row'd in the ſame Galley.</p>
            <p>Sometimes he would lay the fault upon his own bad manage, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon the iron Manners of the Countrey, ſometimes upon his own eaſie inclinations, ſometimes upon the caſe-harden'd temper of the young Lady, and by and by loſt, and confounded with the trouble, (like other miſerable men) he would cry out, and complain of (I know not what) Starrs, and Influences, and Conjunctions, and Aſpects, which (I dare ſay) knew no more of the matter, than the Man in the Moon. Sometimes he fanci'd he had let ſlip the Fatal mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Critical minute in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and that now it was irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and yet when he call'd to mind her preſent rigour, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65788:28"/> his reaſon told him, that that liberty was only ſport, and <hi>Burleſque.</hi> And when he was once about to flatter himſelf with her ſudden indiſpoſition after ſhe had ſeen him the firſt time in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, being told upon enquiry, ſhe had had more of thoſe fits, and remembring how coldly, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concernedly ſhe had entertain'd him upon the Diſcovery, all thoſe thoughts abandon'd, and left him full of ſuſpenſe and irreſolution. While he kept his Chamber, <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> (for more reaſons than he knew) ſent the Governante to make him ſeveral Viſits, though the only way to cure him had been to have come her ſelf. Once as ſhe had deliver'd her Ladies Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment (which was brisk, and Gentile enough) he told her ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that he found ſo much eaſe, and benefit in every-one of theſe welcome Meſſages, that he did
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65788:29"/> really believe, that if her Lady were pleas'd to make a Truce with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ceremonies, and make him one Viſit her ſelf, her preſence would work a Miracle, and ſet him on his feet again in ſpite of his Diſtemper. As ſoon as <hi>Clarinda</hi> had receiv'd this pleaſant Addreſs from her Patient, ſhe (who had no mind he ſhould be loſt for want of ſo ſmall a Favour) went preſently to his Chamber, and with a look full of freedom, and Gallantry told him, that ſince he had deſir'd it, ſhe was come to be his Phyſician. Madam (ſays he,) if you have but brought the will of healing along with you, I ſhall never doubt the cure. Indeed Sir (ſays ſhe,) but I ſhall: For I my ſelf know, that I want one of thoſe two main things, which make a Phyſician complete, That is <hi>Skill,</hi> and you ſuppoſe me to want the other, which is <hi>Honeſty,</hi> and it may be
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65788:29"/> you want that neceſſary qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a hopeful Patient <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo that, methinks, we have a great deal of reaſon to diſtruſt the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. By your pardon, Madam (ſays he,) I can ſee none at all. For if it be true (which they ſay,) that every obſerving man (though no profeſs'd Phyſician) knows readily what ails him, where his Grief lies, and what will do him good, then am I confident of your Ladiſhips Ability in my caſe, And then for my Faith, I am afraid I ſhall carry, but too much of it, to my very Grave. But now, if you ſhould (like ſome of the Faculty, <hi>Pardon the Compariſon</hi>) keep a body in hand, and retard the Cure, either for the advance of ſome ſecret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, or the tryal of ſome curious Experiment, I know not whether I ſhould have more cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of you, for the Cure, or the Wound. So Sir (ſays ſhe) now
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65788:30"/> it's out. Still the old Song, Flames, and Fires, and Darts, and Arrows: If you have nothing elſe to ſay I muſt leave you, leſt inſtead of my curing you, you ſhould infect me, and ſo, Adieu. With that ſhe ſtep'd to the door, and without any parting Solemnity, left the Diſtreſſed <hi>Liſander</hi> ſtudying a Rejoinder. This haughty Carriage of hers brought him a little to himſelf. For now he began to conſider, that 'tis the Adorer makes the Lady a Deity, that a pityful crouching, and ſubmiſſion, only ſerves to make the Ambitious inſolent, and where it does not meet with a true Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, (ſuch as is almoſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the weakneſs of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) does but expoſe the devout to the greater Rigour, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Theſe, and ſome other thoughts of the ſame kind, put the Cane into his hand and led him, as it were in ſpite of Nature, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65788:30"/> his indiſpoſition to take a turn in the Garden. Where he no ſooner ſet his eyes on that Fatal turf, where he diſcover'd his dear <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda,</hi> but the very imagination of her Perſon, her Wit, and her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, call'd him Traytor to his face, and made all this mighty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution vaniſh in an Amorous thought.</p>
            <p>He found ſomething within him that rebell'd againſt his reaſon, and eaſily ſoften'd, and overcame his moſt manly, and beſt adviſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. His Soul was (on the ſudden) once again all Love, and Extaſie, and ſomething he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to do in the proſecution of it, though he knew not what. And though the Enterpriſe every way ſhewed it ſelf very difficult, yet the greatneſs of his Spirit, which could not be baffled with Trifles, and the violence of his Love which was deaf to all denials, prompted
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:65788:31"/> him to go on and proſper, or at worſt to fall and die bravely. He kept his Chamber no longer, though for ſeveral days <hi>Clarinda</hi> gave him no occaſion to ſee her but at the Table, where he could ſay nothing to her, but what the Colonel might hear. Though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all this averſion was but deep Hopocriſie, for ſhe was affected (what pity it was he had not known it) with every word he ſpoke, and every breath he drew, and what ever the ſubject was, he always diſcours'd ſo well, and ſo perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently that every ſentence was his Advocate, and made an impreſſion in her very heart.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing he reſolv'd on was to diſpoſſeſs that unfamiliar Spirit of ſtrangeneſs, which ſhe hugg'd ſo cloſe, and made ſo much of, as well to aſſure her ſelf of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and Sincerity of his Love, as to convince him of the Candour,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65788:31"/> and integrity of her own Honour. The fitteſt means, he could think of to this purpoſe, was an Intrigue with the Governante, whom he met almoſt every day in the Garden. For I muſt acquaint you by the way, that <hi>Clarinda</hi> had hir'd her with a new Gown, and Petticoat, only to appear now and then where he was, in hopes of receiving ſome dear Compliment, or other from him, though but at ſecond hand. The Governante, that very well knew both their minds, chanc'd to be one day in the Garden, where <hi>Liſander,</hi> after a little ſweetning Diſcourſe for a Preface, and her Confidence bought, and paid for with five double Piſtols, acquaints her with his Love to <hi>Clarinda,</hi> and his earneſt deſire of ſome proper juncture to wait upon her alone.</p>
            <p>She ſeem'd to be in a little Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order at the firſt hearing of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65788:32"/> that, (which indeed was no News to her) but the Almighty Gold ſoon compos'd her Spirit, and made her promiſe him her utmoſt aſſiſtance in any honourable Deſign, though ſhe were ſure to incur the eternal diſpleaſure of her Lady. <hi>Of ſuch ſoveraign uſe, and vertue is this Omnipotent Ore in the cloſing of all breaches, and healing all differences between the two Blind Deities of Love, and Fortune.</hi> Hereupon <hi>Clarinda</hi> reſolves, the next day after Dinner, to walk about half a League out of the City to a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-houſe of her Fathers, and the Governante privately acquaints <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> with it in the morning (who had been there two or three times with the Colonel. As ſoon as Dinner was done, he takes a bird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gun in his hand, and about half a mile from the Town (as if it had been by meer accident) he encounters <hi>Clarinda,</hi> and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernante
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:65788:32"/> walking toward the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-houſe. They were both veil'd as the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cuſtom is; and though <hi>Clarinda</hi> paſs'd by him without ſhewing her ſelf, yet the Governante (whom that office bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter became) uncover'd her face, and Saluted him, which oblig'd <hi>Clarinda</hi> in Civility (ſince they were known) to do ſo too. He offer'd her his Attendance in the Walk, and that in ſuch a powerful form of words, that a Lady (leſs inclinable than ſhe) could ſcarce have refus'd him without the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Diſcourteous, and in fine was accepted for their <hi>Salva Guardia.</hi> The Governante pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently put her ſelf (as Gold, and good Clothes, and good Manners oblig'd her) into the Van-Guard, and gave our Lovers all the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Dialogue they could wiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liſander</hi> who had ſuffer'd enough
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:65788:33"/> for one, and now was jealous of loſing another Opportunity, began to tell the Lady that he believ'd Fortune both without his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and merit, had done him this Honour to make him ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for all the Torments he had endur'd for her ſake. If Fortune have made you ſatisfaction (ſays ſhe) then have you nothing to pretend of me. And except you have a mind to make me bad Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and your ſelf troubleſome, Pray let me hear no more of this whining, puling-Love, that makes a man look like one of thoſe Hero's, that is juſt come from killing of a Giant, to lay himſelf down and die, for the frown of a Miſtreſs. For this will never take among people that know the World, and what it is to live, I'll aſſure you. Why then Madam (ſays he) let me tell you once again in the Rhetorick of a Man of War, I am in Love.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65788:33"/> And in haſt too (ſays ſhe) me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, But pray take me along with you, and tell me, whereupon is this Love of yours (that you talk ſo much of) grounded? What do you ſee in this Face, that ſhould make you think me ſuch a Fool, as to believe you can have any real affection for one that has ſo little Merit, and is ſo much a Stranger to you? Madam (ſays he) the ſubject of your Merit is a very large field, and the proſpect is very fair; but becauſe it wants not my Praiſes, and becauſe every man elſe might as well pretend he Loves you for the ſame Cauſe, I will paſs it by only in a ſilent Admiration. But when you ask me how I can Love a Stranger, there you do but beg the Queſtion, and command Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from him, that for your ſake has entirely loſt it. A very fair Confeſſion, Sir, upon my word, (ſays ſhe.) And can you think,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65788:34"/> that a Young Lady ſo Fair, as you ſay, and of ſuch expectation as others ſay I am, ſhould ever be perſuaded to throw her ſelf away upon one that plainly Confeſſes he has loſt his Reaſon? And then to ſay you loſt it for my ſake is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in the ſame mood, and figure with his, that, becauſe he had been Trappan'd for a wound he receiv'd in his Majeſties Service, pretended to be made one of his Privy Council, or anothers, who having loſt his Leg in a Sea-fight againſt the Turk, came to <hi>Madrid</hi> hopping, and hoping to be made one of the Kings Footmen. This will never do your buſineſs, Sir, and till you have more Reaſon, let me intreat you to trouble me with none at all. <hi>Liſander</hi> was almoſt Mad (and it would have made any body ſo) that a man, that wore a Sword, ſhould be run down, at this rate, with a Diſtaff. And
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:65788:34"/> (ſtareing her full in the Face) Madam (ſays he with ſome little heat) you may as well Command me not to breath, or bid my Pulſe ſtand ſtill, as hinder me from Loving, where I ſee I muſt needs repent, though (alaſs!) too late. A certain Demonſtration I have yet Reaſon enough left me to ſee I am miſerable. Thus dull, and inſipid were the poor <hi>Liſanders</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, and he was never in his life known to have ſo little Wit, as now, when he ſtood moſt in need of it. As it often happens to men of good ſenſe, that, when they have a mind to ſpeak beſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver their minds in the moſt proper, and appoſite words, have many times enough to do, to keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves clear of Nonſenſe, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeciſm. <hi>Clarinda</hi> knew well enough, it was the trouble of his mind that made his Wit run ſo muddy, for ſhe had often heard him play the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65788:35"/> Orator, and ſpeak fluently on a dry Subject. At laſt his Paſſion quite ſtopt his Mouth, ſhe had the field to her ſelf, and now ſhe talk'd without an Anſwer. It had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly been a very pleaſant Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment to ſee the Ingenious Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Colonel March on, like one of <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s Undergraduates, all Ears, and no Mouth, and the Lady all the while Philoſophizing to him. Sir (ſays ſhe) (for ſhe never deſign'd he ſhould deſpair) if you be not happy it is your own fault. A wiſe man has more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon his own Fortune and content, than all the Conſtellations of the Firmament, as well thoſe that have beards as thoſe that have none. For where he cannot form his Fortune to his mind, he forms his mind to his Fortune. Thus Happyneſs has oftentimes its foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation in the Opinion, or Deſire, ſo that Deſire without hopes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65788:35"/> a Diſeaſe, To deſire, or take a fancy for what we cannot obtain, is to lay Snares for our ſelves, and to be Authors of our own miſery. When ſhe had finiſh'd this Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue, ſays <hi>Liſander,</hi> like a man that's going to take leave of the World before his time; Let every body take warning by my Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and may Heaven, and good Fortune defend all honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from thoſe Ladies, that have been bred in Cloyſters. With this, and ſuch like Diſcourſe, they paſs'd the time, till they came to the Countrey-houſe, where they had a neat Collation, and a glaſs of Wine in Ice, and ſo home again. All the way homewards <hi>Liſanders</hi> Love was the Ladies Game. It was well for him that Jeers do not go through ones Clothes, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he had (at that time) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd more Wounds, than <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> in the Senate. I will not
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:65788:36"/> undertake to tell you how he found himſelf all this while, I refer you to thoſe Gentlemen, that have ſmarted under the ſame laſh. When they were within half a mile of the City, comes a Gentleman (as if he had been ſent from Heaven for <hi>Liſanders</hi> Deliverance) in his Boots, and Riding-dreſs, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents him a Paper. Which when he had open'd prov'd a Commiſſion from the King for him to go to Sea. Now it is the Cuſtom of <hi>Spain,</hi> for ſome three Months every Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, to ſend five, or ſix Galleys, to ſcowre the Coaſts, and ſecure the Kingdoms of <hi>Naples,</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> and the Places thereabout, from the <hi>Corſairs,</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Pirates. It was for this Service that four Companies were Order'd to be drawn out of that Regiment, and the Lieutenant Colonel to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them. <hi>Liſander</hi> (whoſe will never diſputed with the Kings
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65788:36"/> Service) was well enough ſatisfied with the Honour, though it may be, another, that had Lov'd, as he did, would have receiv'd the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage with ſome ſurpriſe. He was glad to be deliver'd a while from <hi>Clarinda's</hi> Tyranny, and he hop'd that two, or three Months abſence (which has a wonderful Aſcendant over young Lovers) might favour both his Love, and Fortune. As ſoon as they heard <hi>Liſander,</hi> and the Gentleman diſcourſing the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, <hi>Clarinda</hi> turn'd her ſelf round about upon the Governante, and look'd like Death. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante who was afraid ſhe ſhould have fallen down, immediately whiſper'd in her Ear, that ſhe was ſure it was a Deſign, and a Trick only to diſcover her Inclinations. This Invention of the Governante's was very ſudden, and ſeaſonable; for had ſhe ſcratch'd her head for it never ſo little, her Lady had
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65788:37"/> miſcarried, and the Secret had taken Air. But, as ſoon as ſhe heard this, ſhe preſently recover'd the trouble, without the leaſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, the Diſcourſe was ſo earneſt between <hi>Liſander,</hi> and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman. As ſoon as they came into the Houſe, the Governante haſten'd <hi>Clarinda</hi> to her Chamber, for fear ſhe ſhould have met the News again, before ſhe came there. As ſoon as ever they were alone, and the door ſhut, Dear Madam (ſays the Governante) be not ſuppris'd, but the News is moſt true, that the Lieutenant Colonel is to go to Sea, but I perſuaded you in the field, it was not ſo, for fear you ſhould have diſcover'd your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and he have gone away with the Triumph. The Roſes of <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi>'s cheeks crept into their Beds, and all the time of the Governante's Relation, ſhe ſtood ſtill, and ſaid nothing; but as ſoon as the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65788:37"/> had done, ſhe fell a crying, and taking on, like a Woman that had Buried her only Son. Had not the Governante held her, ſhe would have run directly to find her <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> ſo furious was her Love, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all her Coy pretences, and diſſimulation.</p>
            <p>The Governante us'd all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that the Affair in that conjuncture would admit, and all little enough too, to keep her from betraying the violence of her Love, by ways moſt monſtrous and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. At laſt (when <hi>Clarinda</hi> could hear) and the Governante came to tell her, that it was but for two or three months, ſhe was a little better compos'd, and begg'd the Governante to help her to Bed. That night the Governante went to <hi>Liſander</hi> (who was to go about his Commiſſion very early next morning) in her Ladies name, to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:65788:38"/> wiſh him a good Voyage, and a ſafe Return; and told him ſhe was weary with the walk, and in Bed, or ſhe would have waited upon him her ſelf. This was all to diſſemble <hi>Clarinda</hi>'s diſorder, and keep it ſecret between them two. All that night ſhe never laid her eyes together. She roſe more than twenty times, to look for that ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful day, which ſhe fear'd might be the laſt ſhe was ever to ſee her beloved <hi>Liſander.</hi> At length the day broke, and about Sun-riſing the Colonel, and <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> were both before the Gate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Clarinda</hi>'s Window taking leave. They embrac'd one another, and parted (as they were wont upon ſuch occaſions) like good Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers full of joy, and warm hopes. For <hi>Liſander</hi> was going on an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, which was like to bring him both Money and Honour, and for the Dangers he might meet with,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:65788:38"/> he never thought of them before they came, nor talk'd of them when they were once paſs'd. <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> was waiting in her Window, and though it did not become her to ſpeak, yet ſhe bow'd her ſelf, and ſent him away with ſuch paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Wiſhes, as no heart, but one as warm as hers, can ever conceive.</p>
            <p>All the time of his abſence ſhe pleas'd her ſelf with nothing, but thinking and ſpeaking of <hi>Liſander.</hi> She, and the Governante would (I know not how many times a day) be calculating, how far he might be off, how long he had been abſent, and when they might expect his Return. Sometimes they would be muſtering up their pretty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon his Actions, as his Walking, his Speaking, his Salut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his Laughing and his Frown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and another while they would be talking of his Perſon, his Face,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:65788:39"/> his Eyes, his Hair, his Waſt, his Arms, his Hands, his Legs, his Feet, and what not. When they had ſpent ſomething above two months in theſe little Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, News came, that the Kings Galleys were in ſight of <hi>Barcellona,</hi> and homewards bound. They had taken more Prizes, and Priſoners that Summer, than they had in ſeven Summers before, in which Honour <hi>Liſander</hi> had the greateſt ſhare, beſides a Dividend of fifty thouſand pieces of Eight. That part of the Regiment, which ſtay'd behind, was drawn down to the Shore, and receiv'd the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies on board with three Vollies of Shot, who return'd the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement with three more. And thence, as ſoon as they were land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Liſander</hi> led them into the Town, which bad them welcomer than ever they had done any Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in then lives, becauſe they
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65788:39"/> brought Money with them. There was, as much (and more) crowding to ſee <hi>Liſander,</hi> as if they had never ſeen him in their lives. And as he march'd through the Streets, in the head of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, there was as many Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows open, as it had been at a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation. The Colonel was at that time at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and was to ſtay there five or ſix weeks to receive Inſtructions and Money for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruiting his Regiment, which had ſuffer'd great loſs in the Wars of <hi>Flanders.</hi> So that <hi>Liſander</hi> choſe rather to provide himſelf Quarters in another Houſe, than to give the World the leaſt occaſion to cenſure, either his Prudence, or the young Ladies Conduct in her Fathers ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. <hi>Clarinda</hi> was more ſenſible of <hi>Liſanders</hi> Honour, and affected with his good Fortune, than he was himſelf; and therefore the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante advis'd her to keep her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65788:40"/> as well for fear of being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad when he came to Viſit, as for fear of diſcovering the Fire in her Heart, by the light of her Countenance. And yet it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd between them, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they knew they had him faſt, or to ſee how much a great Spirit could bear, ſhe ſhould ſhew him but juſt the ſame Curtezy, and receive him with the very ſame Civility that ſhe would do a meer Stranger. <hi>Alaſs, that any honeſt mans Quiet and Satisfaction ſhould be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by the falſe weights, and meaſures, by the Hypocriſie, and Diſſimulation of a cruel, and ill-natur'd Woman!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every body that knock'd at the Gate alarm'd <hi>Clarinda</hi> with the ſame tranſport, and ſurprize, as if it had been <hi>Liſander</hi> himſelf, for, whoever knock'd, ſhe ſtill fancy'd it was he. The next day, about
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:65788:40"/> two of the Clock, when he thought no body could either ſuſpect, or obſerve his haſt, he went to make his dear <hi>Clarinda</hi> a Viſit. She had already reſolv'd the manner of his Entertainment, which was this: She met, and receiv'd him in her Antichamber, ſuffer'd him to kiſs her hand, and ſo led him into her Chamber. After ſhe had diſcours'd him a while, ſhe ſate her down upon her <hi>Eſtrado,</hi> and left this Child of Fortune to Court her ſtanding upon his feet, with his Hat under his Arm.</p>
            <p>After he had ſignified his ſenſe of the Colonels Abſence, and then Comforted both her, and himſelf with the great neceſſity, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of it, he began by gentle degrees, to make her new Tenders of his old Services. The Fame, and Succeſs of his Voyage, and his fair reception inſpir'd him with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65788:41"/> mighty hopes, that now his hand was in, he ſhould carry his Miſtreſs too. The torrent of his words was brisker, and more luxuriant, than it us'd to be, and one would have thought, he had reſerv'd the choice Meditations of two whole Months, and more, for this very occaſion. I need not tell you what effect his <hi>Rhetorick</hi> had upon <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda's</hi> Spirit, but certainly it was ſuch, as no Lady in the world, but her ſelf, could have diſſembled. The moment of <hi>Liſanders</hi> happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and her yielding was not yet come, and therefore with three, or four Sentences, and as many grave Regards ſhe Anſwer'd him, That ſhe was very ſenſible he was a perſon every way compleat, and hanſom, and that his Character, and Employment had been always ſuch, as might render any man conſiderable. That his late Naval Service had won him old Gold, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:65788:41"/> new Lawrels, and for ever enroll'd his Name among the Favourites of Fame, and Fortune. That for theſe reaſons, he would do well to think of ſome Amours, that might be more to his advantage, and if theſe conſiderations would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with him to deſiſt, ſhe aſſur'd him, that beſides the inequality of their Fortunes, ſhe had already diſpos'd of her Heart, and could not by any means think of altering her Reſolutions. <hi>Liſander</hi> heard all this with the very ſame looks, that a Convicted Priſoner receives the Sentence of his Death. Little did he think where ſhe had diſpos'd her heart, nor would the Agony give him leave, ſo much as once to imagine, it might fall to his ſhare. But as ſoon, as his cold fit was over, he told her ſuddenly, and with a heat little leſs than that of Anger, how ill ſhe had requited all his paſt Services; and that if his Deſpair
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65788:42"/> did not prove Mortal, he would hereafter ſtudy to take ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, as might give neither of them ſo much trouble, or diſquiet. Sir (ſays ſhe) I do extremely applaud your Reſolution, and I know no other Expedient that can reſtore the great Opinion, I have always had, of your Conduct, and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Thus did <hi>Liſander</hi> take his leave, reſolving to maintain no other Familiarity with her, for the future, than what might juſt vindicate him from the imputation of ill breeding.</p>
            <p>That ſame night, that he might ſeem to take his leave Gentilely, he brought two, or three of his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who were excellent Muſitians, and his Confidents, before <hi>Clarin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da's</hi> Lodgings, to give her this parting Serenade under the name of <hi>Chloris.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65788:42"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CHloris</hi> your Rigour was to blame,</l>
                  <l>Your Ice hath chill'd, and quench'd my flame;</l>
                  <l>Your Anger hath my heat allay'd,</l>
                  <l>Your Scorn hath cur'd the wound your Beauty made,</l>
                  <l>I'll Sigh, and Vow no more in vain,</l>
                  <l>You've freed a Captive by too ſtrait a Chain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I can your Pride no longer bear,</l>
                  <l>No longer hope, no longer fear,</l>
                  <l>The Arrow's fallen from my ſide,</l>
                  <l>Deſpair has done, what Love, and You deni'd,</l>
                  <l>My Paſſion's Murder'd in your hate,</l>
                  <l>And tho you'd Love me now, yet 'tis too late.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>This was the pleaſanteſt Scene in the world to <hi>Clarinda,</hi> and the Governante, who were well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>Liſanders</hi> Paſſion, and knew it was not in his power to ſtay away above two, or three days at moſt. They were ready to fall down with laughing to ſee him Cock his Hat, and act the Cruel, that, for all this appearance, would at the ſame time have fallen down on both his knees for a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65788:43"/> and have broke all the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to boot, with all his heart, for conſenting to the Song.</p>
            <p>However, to make her believe he was in good earneſt, and to try whether he could make <hi>Clarinda</hi> jealous, the very next night he went, and made Love in another place. It was a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Addreſs to a young Lady of Quality, perform'd upon the Street (as the manner is) juſt before her Lodgings. He meaſur'd the ground, more than a hundred times backward, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, with many a falſe, languiſhing look toward the poor abuſed Lady in the Window. He had two of the hardeſt parts to Act, at that time, that ever any man in the world undertook, to pretend a falſe Paſſion, and diſſemble a true one. The poor Lady was ſo pleas'd with <hi>Liſanders</hi> Service (for all the Town knew him) that had not Modeſty,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65788:43"/> and the Cuſtom of the Nation reſtrain'd her, ſhe could never have ſtood to make more than two words to the bargain, here's the one, here's the other, and ee'n have let him in to rights.</p>
            <p>She began in the ſpace of two, or three nights application, to value her ſelf, not ſo much upon her own, as upon the merit of <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and made no more difficulty of entertaining his Love, than one, that had faſted three days, would to go to dinner.</p>
            <p>In the mean while <hi>Clarinda</hi> who had ſtill the news of all that paſs'd, was reſolved to ſail with the ſame wind, to entertain another ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and ſee whether he, or ſhe could brook a Rival with leſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience. Having reſolv'd on the Deſign ſhe communicated it to the Governante, who was the beſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65788:44"/> Manager of ſuch an Intrigue, that could be, and ſo they preſently pitched upon the Gentleman. There was a Gentleman, you muſt know, that in <hi>Liſanders</hi> abſence, had made two, or three attempts to no purpoſe, to inſinuate himſelf into <hi>Clarinda</hi>'s ſervice, and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cholerick with the diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which is the moſt unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable weakneſs a man can be guilty of) was bold to name the Lady, without that reſpect, and tenderneſs which were the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable dues of her Vertue, and Diſcretion. The words in the proper and uſual ſence ſignifi'd well enough, but, becauſe they were ambiguous, and capable of a bad Conſtruction (which it may be he deſign'd) he was thought the fitteſt man in the World to be <hi>Liſander</hi>'s Rival. For they could not but ſuſpect, that when <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> came to underſtand his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:65788:44"/> he would certainly grow impatient, and his Paſſion might at once revenge his own, and <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi>'s wrongs, in giving his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall the <hi>Baſtinado.</hi> The Deſign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus laid, the next morning they met the Cavalier at Maſs where (never dreaming that ſhe knew how he had injur'd her) he was almoſt raviſh'd, to See <hi>Clarinda</hi> caſt now, and then an amorous Glance upon him, as it were by ſtealth, and as if ſhe were afraid to be ſeen. He began to conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had alter'd his Garb, or ſhe her mind, but wherever the Secret lay, he was ſure ſhe had conceiv'd ſome advantageous ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of his Perſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Wiſdom thought it fit to puſh his good fortune, and ſtrike while the Iron was hot. As they were coming out of the Church, ſhe look'd back upon him again, which ſufficiently confirm'd his
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65788:45"/> opinion, and made him reſolve to go Serenade her that very night. The good Gentleman ſpent the whole day in providing himſelf of four of the beſt Muſitians, that were to be had in the City, to grace the ſolemnity. And, at night, full of expectation, he made a fine <hi>Parade</hi> with his Fidlers before her window, where he began to Sing her ſuch a parcel of doggerel Couplet, of his own making, as might very well have given him a right to a good drub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, though he had never done any thing elſe amiſs in all his life. <hi>Liſander,</hi> who had his Spyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, preſently got notice of it, as he was practiſing Love in the next ſtreet, Sacrificing whole <hi>Hecatombs</hi> of flying Kiſſes, and paying a thouſand ſilent ſpeaking Reverences to his new Saint. You muſt pardon him, if he took his leave a little abruptly; for the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65788:45"/> counterfeit Paſſion, he had for his new Miſtreſs, eaſily gave place to the true one he had for his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val. Leſt the Serenaders ſhould have loſt their labour, away he goes in all haſt, attended only by two of his own Souldiers, that brought him the intelligence, who were truſty fellows, and excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in a doubtful occaſion. As ſoon as ever they came up with the Muſick, without any other greeting, at a matter of half a dozen blows, they broke two fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and as many heads, whereof his Rival's chanc'd to be one. This Adventure was one of the ſtilleſt (of a rough one) that ever I heard of. The Enemy took the retreat without ſo much as ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what's the meaning of this? So that there was not one word of complaint, or controverſie, nor the leaſt noiſe in the World, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that of the ſtaves. For <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:65788:46"/> came not to fight and quarrel, but to correct, and chaſtiſe, and the poor Fidlers were ſo frighted with the ſurpriſe, that they quite forgot they had any ſwords on. <hi>Clarinda,</hi> who was a party in the action and ſaw all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it, from her window, better than they that perform'd it, was better pleas'd than ever ſhe was with any thing in all her life. And as ſoon as ſhe could for laughing, ſhe vow'd to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernante, that the Gentlemans Diſhonour ſhould for ever excuſe her from ſhewing him the leaſt favour. But ſhe might have ſpar'd that breath, for <hi>Don</hi> was a <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> and was ſo much aſham'd to have ſuffer'd ſuch an affront, and ſo tamely before his Miſtreſs, that he durſt ſooner thought of dying, than of ever coming in to her ſight again.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:65788:46"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Liſander</hi> having by this action confeſſed the power of his Love, and his impotence to diſſemble it, preſented himſelf the next day to <hi>Clarinda,</hi> made a profound ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and beg'd her pardon. She found her own ſtrength, and his weakneſs, and intending to make her own uſe of both, ſhe told him, that his relation to the <hi>Colonell,</hi> and his own merit, ſhould at any ſeaſonable hours open him the doors of that Houſe, and make him welcome as a Friend; But if he ſtill perſiſted to pretend any farther, ſhe muſt be forc'd to make uſe of thoſe Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, which ſhe was not willing to think of. <hi>Liſander</hi> had enough to ſay, but durſt not anſwer one word at that time, for fear of moving her diſpleaſure, which was more terrible to him, than a Cannon in a breach, charg'd with ſmall ſhot. However he ſtill frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:65788:47"/> the Houſe, and was as familiar there as if he had been at home. And though it was directly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden him, yet when he found <hi>Clarinda</hi> in a good humor, he could not chuſe but give the old ſtring now and then a gentle touch, and let her ſee by Some paſſing Trope that his Love was above her rigour. When he ſpoke ſo plain that ſhe was oblig'd to take notice of it, he was ſure to loſe her Company for that time, which made him day, and night beat his brains, and weary himſelf to find out ſome deſperate Remedy, that might either kill, or cure; Some Expedient to ſet <hi>Clarinda</hi> on the rack, and force her with one breath to determine the ſucceſs of his weary Love. For a downright Deſpair, he knew could make him dy but once, whereas, that doubtful hope, that temper'd Cruelty, thoſe corrected Poyſons,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:65788:47"/> made him ready to give up the Ghoſt once, or twice a day. And what gave him very wonderful apprehenſions, his utmoſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence could never yet learn, who (as ſhe told him) ſhe had diſpos'd of her Heart; for he never heard, that ſhe entertain'd any Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but himſelf. In the midſt of this perplexity, Love, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, who had long pittyed his ſufferings laid their heads together, and undertook his Deliverance, which was thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liſander</hi> having a mind to ſee the Regiment together, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe them, Commanded them to be in Arms by the Sea-ſhore next morning at the opening of the Gates. It happen'd the ſame Evening, that four tall Ships were come to anchor near the ſhore to take in freſh water, and as ſoon as ever it was light in the morning,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:65788:48"/> loos'd their foretop-ſails, and were weighing anchor, intending with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two hours to be under Sail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <hi>Liſander</hi> who was upon the ſhore with the Regiment, gave his Captain Commandant inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions what to do, till he came back, and went privately into the City to try his laſt practice upon <hi>Clarinda.</hi> He came up to her Chamber door, and knock'd in more haſt than he us'd to do, and the Governante opened him the door; for her Lady was juſt up. As ſoon as he enter'd the room, the Governante withdrew, imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he might have ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary buſineſs, becauſe it was ſo early, and he ſeem'd to be in ſuch haſt. Now Madam (ſays he) to <hi>Clarinda,</hi> I am come to take my leave of you, and (as I have often done in jeſt) bid you Farewel for ever, in good earneſt. And with that he led her to the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65788:48"/> ſhew'd her the Regiment on the Shore, the Ships with their fore-topſails looſe, and their anchors on peak. And then told her, that, laſt night late, he had received News, that there were great appearances of another War with <hi>France,</hi> and an Order to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barque, in thoſe Ships with the Regiment for <hi>Flanders</hi> again, where the Colonell was to meet them.</p>
            <p>That he had not a moment to ſtay, but beg'd her a thouſand pardons for all the indiſcretions, which his paſſionate Love might ever have been guilty of, and wiſh'd her all the ſatisfaction ſhe could ever hope, or promiſe her ſelf in her own unmovable Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Clarinda</hi> during this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, turn'd her eyes, I know not how many times, from <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to the Ships, and from the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:65788:49"/> Ships to <hi>Liſander.</hi> And ſeeing the trouble, and confuſion he was in, (which indeed was for fear his Project ſhould have miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd) She threw her arms about his neck, and fell on weeping moſt pittifully. Had it been to ſave both their lives, She could not have ſpoken one word; but with the ſame hold, She kiſs'd him a thouſand times, and wet all his face with her tears. <hi>Liſander</hi> ſeeing the fury of her Paſſion, began to miſtruſt the Effects of it, and was ready to repent the Experiment. And though he knew there was no reaſon for it, yet he could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt have found in his heart to have wept for company. Dear Madam (ſays he) ſpeak, and let me go. Never, Never, my dear <hi>Liſander</hi> (ſays ſhe,) and ſo ſhe fell on weeping again with that violence that ſhe could not get out another word. As ſoon as ſhe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:65788:49"/> was come a little to her ſelf, Falſe, and perfidious man (ſays ſhe) could thy Cruelty find no other way to put an end to this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life of mine? Is this the fruit of all your Vows, and Oaths? Is this indeed the end of all your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Love, and Conſtancy? Dear <hi>Liſander</hi> let me in pitty die by your hand to prevent that more cruell, and unfortunate death, which I ſhall meet in your abſence. Madam (ſays he, with no little amazement,) If all this be Love, it is either very young, or you have been extremely in the wrong to diſſemble it all this while. For now, Dear Madam I muſt tell you, the time is paſs'd, and 'tis too late to recall it. Bear your fate, as well as you may, though I am ſure in a very little time to ſink under mine. And whereas a ſeaſonable freedom might have made us both happy,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:65788:50"/> this ill-tim'd Love of yours, worſe than Diſdain, ſhews it ſelf too late, like a flaſh of Gunpowder after the Execution is done. May my grief, and hard fate (ſays ſhe) light on them, that firſt impos'd this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie modeſty, this ſelf-murdering reſervation upon the frailty of our Sexe. I have lov'd you, my Dear <hi>Liſander,</hi> as my own Soul, ever ſince the firſt time I ſaw you; it is to you I have diſpos'd my Heart, and methinks a man of your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, might have read as much in my very Eyes. <hi>Dear Liſander,</hi> either ſtay here, or take me with you, or do ſomething — and then her ſorrow interrupted her again, that ſhe could go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Madam (ſays he) I had been the happieſt of all mortal men, had I but known you Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions a little ſooner; but it's now to late. I can neither take you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with me, nor yet diſobey
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:65788:50"/> the Kings Order, and ſtay here. All I can ſay, is this, If I have but one half hours leaſure, before we ſet Sail, I will wait upon you again to receive your laſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. With that they kiſs'd, and Embrac'd one another once again, and ſo they parted. As ſoon as <hi>Liſander</hi> was gone the Governante came in, and found the ſorrowful Lady groveling upon the bed, with her face towards the pillow, ſtriving in vain to ſtiffle that Grief, which was now grown ſtubborn, and unruly. She was a good while before ſhe could tell her the ſad tidings, which when ſhe had ended, ſhe fell on raving, and curſing the advice, and conduct of all ſuch Governantes. Poor <hi>Leonora</hi> knew not what to ſay or do. She would have told her, as ſhe did the laſt time in the field, that it was all meer deſign, and fiction, but ſhe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:65788:51"/> foreſaw, that Wheadle was not like to paſs twice. And finding her Lady utterly incapable both of comfort, and counſel, ſhe told her, ſhe would ſtep down to the ſhore, and inform her ſelf better. That it may be, things were not altogether ſo deſperate, as ſhe fancy'd them; and if there were any thing left to hope, they would leave nothing unattempted, that might contribute to her ſatisfaction. <hi>Drowning men catch at any thing.</hi> And ſeeing the Governante had yet ſome little heart, <hi>Clarinda</hi> rais'd her face a little from the Pillow, and bade her go. The Governante made fewer ſtrides to to the ſhore, than ever ſhe did in her life (though it were to an Aſſignation.) And finding a huge croud of people there (who were come to ſee the Regiment Exerciſe) and ſeeing Marriners ſo buſie at work ſhe never ſo much as doubted
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:65788:51"/> the truth of <hi>Liſander</hi>'s Relation. As ſoon as ever an occaſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it ſelf, ſhe ſaluted one of thoſe Officers, which I was tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you were <hi>Liſanders</hi> Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and wiſhed him a fair Wind and a good voyage. What do ye mean Madam (ſays he?) I mean to <hi>Flanders</hi> Sir (ſays ſhe.) Not this year I hope (ſays he) Madam, we were there but too lately. Pray Sir (ſays ſhe) whither are you bound then? No whither Madam (ſays he) that I know, but to Exerciſe. And juſt then the Lieutenant Colonel call'd him to his command. This Officer preſently imagin'd there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the bottom of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes diſcourſe, but he thought it inconſiſtent with his diſcretion to ſound her, or enquire any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Governante run home again like lightning, and by the way two or three of her acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:65788:52"/> asked her, if ſhe had been to ſee the Regiment Exerciſe, which confirm'd her, that the Story of returning to <hi>Flanders</hi> was but one of <hi>Liſanders</hi> Practices upon the Lady. The good News drove her home again in as much haſt, as the fright had driven her abroad, and had it not been for drawing the boys after her, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſhe had gone faſter. As ſoon as ever ſhe came into the Chamber, Courage Madam (ſays ſhe) Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, And when ſhe had breath enough, She told her, We are abus'd, Madam. There is no ſuch thing. The Regiment is not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on board: It is only exerciſing upon the ſhore. And if you pleaſe to come to the window here, you may ſee them, (For till then ſhe durſt ſcarce have look'd out, though a look would have ſtay'd the Regiment.) It was then, that <hi>Clarinda</hi> firſt began to reflect
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:65788:52"/> upon <hi>Liſanders</hi> Policy, and her own weakneſs. And going to the window, ſhe ſaw the Ships ſail, and the Regiment continue their Exerciſe upon the ſhore. The tacite ſhame, and ſenſe of her diſhonour was almoſt as troubleſome, as if the Regiment had ſail'd indeed. Sometimes ſhe fancy'd it a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon her from the God of Love, (if there be any ſuch Deity) for her hypocriſie in his ſervice and her bad uſage of <hi>Liſander.</hi> Sometimes ſhe thought <hi>Liſander</hi> had but pay'd her her own, and that his Revenge was but juſt. And ſometimes ſhe was in pain to think, how ſhe ſhould receive him the next time he came. When the Exerciſe was done, and <hi>Liſander</hi> had led the Regiment to the Market-Place, and diſcharg'd them, they ſaw him give his Pike to his ſervant, and come directly towards her Lodgings. She bade the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernante
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65788:53"/> ſtep to the door, and tell him, her Lady was not well. The Governante did ſo; to whom he made no other reply, but, that he was ſorry for it, and ſent her his ſervice, and ſo march'd off. This Excuſe (as he look'd upon it) of her indiſpoſition, madded him to the very heart, and made him reſolve, now he knew her ſecret, that he would never ſee her again, till he was ſent for. Three days, and three nights did theſe Lovers keep their points, each of them expecting the other ſhould addreſs firſt. In the end <hi>Liſander</hi> had the better of it, and let her ſee what it was for a Woman to ſlight a Perſon whom ſhe lov'd. She could endure no longer than the fourth day, and then ſhe ſent the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernante early in the morning, to meet him at Maſs, and invite him to her Lodgings. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante did ſo, and he promis'd he
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:65788:53"/> would come, though he told her it could not be till afternoon, for he was engag'd to dine with a Friend.</p>
            <p>This was a little ſtrange ta <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda,</hi> for ſhe had known the time when he would not have deferr'd the favour, to have din'd with an Emperor. About four of the Clock he came, and the Governante (as ſhe was Commanded) went forth of the Chamber, as ſhe let him in. <hi>Clarinda</hi> was ſitting upon her <hi>Eſtrado</hi> at her Needle, where <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander</hi> with a Smile march'd up to her, and Saluted her, which ſhe return'd with a grave, and Modeſt regard. She had not yet determin'd what to do, or how to behave her ſelf, but look'd very Penſive and Melancholy, and whatever he ſaid, ſhe Anſwer'd him all along with a Monoſyllable, and Sennor. At length Madam (ſays he) if I
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:65788:54"/> thought my Preſence made your Ladyſhip uneaſie, I would take my leave. With that ſhe ſtuck her needle in her Work, and looking him full in the face. Sir (ſays ſhe) Wherein have I deſerv'd to be us'd ſo like one of your <hi>Gallina's?</hi> Or what have I done, that you could think of expoſing my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thus? What is become of all that pretended Paſſion, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Tenderneſs of yours? Or where is that reſpect, and Civility, which in Juſtice all Gentlemen of your Character owe the Ladies? But I Confeſs it is too good for me. My eaſineſs at the firſt Interview, made you think me fit to receive impreſſions, and all my ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſince that minute, could never ſet me right again in your Opinion. In vain, Alas! were the holy Siſters ſo many years in building, and adorning a Structure, which this falſe Ingrate has in a moment
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:65788:54"/> ruin'd, and laid in the duſt. In vain have they inculcated the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of our Sex, and read me ſo many Lectures of Decency, and Modeſty, which were all but like words written on a Wave, or like the Faith, and Promiſes of this Wretch, whoſe Deceit, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery has taken, and demoliſh'd all the Out-works of my Honour, and left me nothing (Alas!) which I can call my own, but the Maiden-Caſtle. And then ſhe fell a weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which gave <hi>Liſander</hi> time to Anſwer. Madam (ſays he) when you have heard me ſpeak, if you think it fit, it will be time enough to Condemn me. What Error have I Committed, in making you Confeſs a truth, the concealment whereof (for ought I know) might have prov'd Fatal to us both, and have coſt us much dearer, than the Diſcovery? And as long as I am juſt, and honourable (that is as long as
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:65788:55"/> I live) how can I think of expoſing your weakneſs? The Secret is among our ſelves, and, without you ſhall think meet to Diſcover it, is like to remain ſo. And now you ſee how forc'd, and unnatural the <hi>Siſters</hi> Breeding is: How inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thoſe Cuſtoms are, that oblige us to diſſemble our ſtrongeſt deſires, to ſlight what we Love, and run away from our own Happyneſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas, Madam, you ſeem to find your ſelf afflicted, for the indecency (as you are pleas'd to call it) of this laſt Accident, and may ſuſpect it may have ſome untoward Influence upon my Love, I will tell you, Madam, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as my Paſſion was always true, and ſincere, yet before, it wanted this to make it complete, to know I was belov'd. And now, Madam (that you have ſeen the vanity of it) if you pleaſe to ſet aſide all ſtarch'd Behaviour, and <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:65788:55"/> Formality, Let us be friends, and never fall out again; for I Love you better than ever I did, and will do ſo whilſt I breath.</p>
            <p>At theſe words ſhe threw down her ſeam, and riſing up haſtily, ſhe threw her Arms about his Neck, and Kiſs'd him with as much tenderneſs, as ſhe had done when he pretended to return for <hi>Flanders.</hi> My dear <hi>Liſander</hi> (ſays ſhe) we have eſcap'd the Storm, and are now in ſafe Harbour, where we may ſecurely pity, or laugh at the Diſtreſs of thoſe, that muſt yet make ſport for <hi>Neptune,</hi> and the Winds. We have nothing left us now to do, but to Enjoy one another, and be Happy. And ſo ſhe took the willing <hi>Liſander</hi> by the hand, and made him ſit down by her upon her <hi>Eſtrado.</hi> I ſhall (for good Conſiderations) take no notice what farther Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might paſs between this happy Pair. Nor would I have
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:65788:56"/> any longing Lover ſo much as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know. They were both perſons, that underſtood themſelves well, and therefore it would be rude to doubt, or enquire into their Conduct. <hi>Liſander</hi> continued his Viſits, juſt as he us'd to do, and yet when there happen'd to be any Strangers by, he kept as great a diſtance, and us'd as much caution, and diligence in his Behaviour, as he did in the firſt of their Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But when they were alone. their Converſation was free, and Gallant, and had no reſervation in it, but ſuch as ſerv'd to heighten their Pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Sometimes they entertain'd one another with the curious Story of their Amours. Sometimes he frighted her into his Arms, with the terrible Relation of ſome deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Adventure in the War. And ſometimes ſhe drew him into hers,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:65788:56"/> with ſome ſoft, and melting Air upon the Lute, which ſhe touch'd to Admiration, and Charm'd him with ſome Paſſionate Song.</p>
            <p>I cannot omit to give you one of them, wherein ſhe does moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently Paint her own Paſſion, and (as far as the Cauſe would bear it) Apologize for her own Infirmity. It was perform'd one calm Evening in a cloſe Walk in the Garden, when ſhe had call'd for her Lute, and diſmiſs'd the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. The words were theſe:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HOw oft have I vow'd, that no Mortal ſhould move</l>
                     <l>The pityleſs Heart of <hi>Clarinda</hi> to Love?</l>
                     <l>Yet in ſpite of my peeviſh Averſion, I ſee</l>
                     <l>That in vain we reſiſt, what the Gods do decree.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:65788:57"/>
                     <l>How many Brisk Gallants, both in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and jeſt,</l>
                     <l>In vain have pretended a room in this Breſt,</l>
                     <l>Which a Souldier of Fortune, aſſiſted by none</l>
                     <l>But his Valour, and Fate, has eternally wonne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No Laurels, <hi>O Cupid,</hi> to your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering Bow,</l>
                     <l>'Tis <hi>Mars,</hi> and not you, that has giv'n me the blow,</l>
                     <l>Nor am I the firſt, that has open'd her Arms,</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Venus</hi> thou know'ſt, to a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours Charms.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I acknowledge, <hi>Liſander,</hi> 'tis too late for the Town</l>
                     <l>To treat of Conditions, now the Walls are your own,</l>
                     <l>Yet the ruins of my vanquiſhed Virtue ſtill cry,</l>
                     <l>Uſe your Conqueſt with Honour, or know I can dye.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:65788:57"/>
            <p>But the Heaven was too clear, and the Weather too calm to continue long ſo, And when their Bliſs had once arriv'd at its <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> you cannot but expect it ſhould decline again. Within the ſpace of one Month the Hony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to loſe its Taſt, and both their Paſſions began to loſe ſomething of their Warmth, and Vigour. There was neither of them ſo fond of the others Company, as they us'd to be, though they were both willing to Conceal it. I know not whether they had ſurfeited of their own Happyneſs, or whether ſome ſecret Guilt, or remorſe made their Love irkſome, and imbitter'd the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but certain it is, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity they had Contracted by theſe tedious, and difficult Methods, did (like a Rivulet exhauſted by the Summer Sun) inſenſibly begin to fail, and reſolve its ſelf into its firſt Elements of Strangeneſs; ſo
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:65788:58"/> that neither of them car'd, how ſeldom they met, but for fear of diſobliging the other. It chanc'd in the mean time that an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seaman brought <hi>Liſander</hi> a Letter, of ſome eight Months date, from his Dear, and Virtuous <hi>Sabina,</hi> to whom he had plighted his firſt Vows, and whom in all his Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries he had never forgot. The Contents were theſe:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Sabina</hi> to <hi>Liſander.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>My Dear</hi> Liſander,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IF this Paper ſhould chance to come to your hand, believe it when it tells you, your <hi>Sabina</hi> is weary of the world, and would hate the very Light, but that ſhe flatters her ſelf, it will once again ſhew her her Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>Liſander:</hi> If it never reach you, it does but follow the Fate of a hundred of its Brethren, who (I
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:65788:58"/> know by your delays) have loſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as well as I) in the enquiry, and furniſh'd matter of laughter, to thoſe they were never intended for. Too too fatal Emblems (alas!) of my Misfortune, and full of Love, and Impatience, as any thing in the world but the poor Heart of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Diſtreſſed <hi>Sabina.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſame Moment that he read this Letter, he reſolv'd upon his return, and began to think of an excuſe for his long Abſence. And calling for Pen, and Ink, he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the Seaman (who was home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bound) this Anſwer:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:65788:59"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Liſander</hi> to <hi>Sabina.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>
                           <hi>My own Dear</hi> Sabina.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>AS ſoon as I had open'd yours, I found my own thoughts ſo well Expreſs'd, that I had like to have Tranſcrib'd it, and (having chang'd only the name) ſent it back again in Anſwer. I will only add, that Love, and Impatience have made me reſolve, to tell you very ſpeedily in Perſon, that it is not in the power of Seas and Mountains any longer to ſeparate, and keep alive two Bodies, that have but one Soul. Courage (my dear <hi>Sabina</hi>) and the joy which ſparkles in your Eyes, ſhall like ſome propitious Star, ſerve to light me back again through the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:65788:59"/> Ocean, and forever after influence all the Happyneſs of.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your own <hi>Liſander.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Immediately in order to his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, he diſpatch'd another Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Colonel, to ſatisfie him of his Reſolution, and deſire him to procure him his Majeſties Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, and for ſome Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his own enjoyn'd him all the Secreſie, the Affair was capable of. The Colonel (having loſt all hopes of having <hi>Liſander</hi> his Son-in-Law.) wrote <hi>Clarinda</hi> word, that he had provided her a Husband at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and Commanded her to prepare for her Journey thither, within fourteen days.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Letters of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, and <hi>Sabina</hi> were receiv'd by
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:65788:60"/> our Lovers with equal joy, and conceal'd from one another with equal induſtry; and both of them make private preparations for their ſeveral Journeys. <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> preſently wrote to her Father, that he would take no notice to any body of the Match, becauſe the event was yet uncertain, and ſo he never ſo much as mention'd it in his Letter to <hi>Liſander.</hi> About fourteen days afterwards, in the ſame Pacquet (Directed to <hi>Liſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>) came the Kings Diſcharge, and the Ladies Commands to ſet forth for <hi>Madrid.</hi> They both began their Journey on the ſame day, and both under falſe Colours, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. And though they had been both very well content with the whole truth, yet neither of them durſt begin to declare. They were each of them very ſparing in asking Queſtions about the others Journey, for fear of being oblig'd
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:65788:60"/> to Anſwer ſome about their own.</p>
            <p>At parting they took a very For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, and Compos'd leave without the leaſt Tranſport or Paſſion, at which they both extremely won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd. After parting the only thing they were each of them very ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous about, was the great trouble, and perplexity which would ſeize upon the other, when the Myſtery came to be reveal'd. <hi>Liſander</hi> doubted how poor <hi>Clarinda</hi> would receive the News of his Departure for <hi>England,</hi> and her greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction was, to think how he would endure to hear of her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Liſander</hi> came to <hi>Paris,</hi> he was inform'd by Letters in the Poſt-office from the Colonel (for all things were now concluded, and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:65788:61"/> made Publick) that his Daughter was happyly Marri'd, which made <hi>Liſander</hi> finiſh his Journey to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> with great ſatisfaction. And the Colonel had told <hi>Clarinda</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her Arrival, that <hi>Liſander</hi> had got his Diſcharge and was gone for <hi>England,</hi> which remov'd the Secret grief, and trouble which would otherwiſe have been part of the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of her Marriage-bed. He was not many days before he Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at <hi>Dover,</hi> with about threeſcore thouſand pieces of Eight in Bills of Exchange, and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gold, a Gentleman, Four men in Livery, and Seven Choſen <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Horſes. He was receiv'd at <hi>Dover,</hi> by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral both of his own, and <hi>Sabina's</hi> Friends who had notice of his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution by the Poſt, and were well agreed on all ſides about the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, which now wanted nothing, but the Conſummation.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:65788:61"/>
            <p>When he came to <hi>London,</hi> he was Conducted to <hi>Sabina's</hi> Lodging, and very ſplendidly Entertain'd, where the overjoy'd Lady threw her ſelf into his Arms, and in the Extaſie could not ſpeak one word beſide, <hi>Welcome, my Dear</hi> Liſander.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:62"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of ſome Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Henry Faithorne,</hi> and <hi>John Kerſey,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>THe Caſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> briefly and truly Stated, in the three firſt and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Principles of a Chriſtian Church: I. The obligation of Chriſtianity, by Divine Right. II. The Jurisdiction of the Church, by Divine Right. III. The Inſtitution of Epiſcopal Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority, by Divine Right. By <hi>S. P.</hi> a Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in 80.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Summum Bonum, ſeu vera, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Unica Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo Hominibus per Chriſtum Communicanda, Sex Diſſertationibus aliquatenus explicata: Per Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundum Eliſium, Eccleſiae Anglicanae Presbyterum.</hi> 80. Price Bound 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomons</hi> Song Paraphras'd: a Pindarick Poem. 40. Price Stitcht 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ephemeri Vita,</hi> or the Natural Hiſtory and Anatomy of the <hi>Ephemeron,</hi> a Fly that lives but five hours. Written originally in <hi>Low-Dutch</hi> by <hi>Jo. Swammerdam,</hi> M. D. of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in 40.</p>
            <p>Mathematical Magick: or the Wonders that may be performed by Mechanical Geometry, In two Books, Concerning Mechan.
<list>
                  <item>Powers,</item>
                  <item>Motions,</item>
               </list> being one of the moſt eaſie, pleaſant, uſeful (and yet moſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected) part of Mathematicks. Not before Treated of in this Language. By <hi>J. Wilkins,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> 80.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65788:62"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
